<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Archana Vaidheeswaran</title>
        <description>Creative Portfolio Theme for Jekyll.</description>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
        <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Mon, 19 Jun 2023 19:28:16 +0800</pubDate>
        <lastBuildDate>Mon, 19 Jun 2023 19:28:16 +0800</lastBuildDate>
        <generator>Jekyll v4.3.2</generator>
        
            <item>
                <title>Journey of a South Asian Woman in Tech- Breaking Barriers &amp; Bridging Disparities</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;As a South Asian woman with over five years of experience in data science and artificial intelligence, I’ve realized that my journey in the tech world is anything but ordinary. I am a data product manager with Women Who Code in Singapore. However, the path to where I am today was filled with obstacles and challenges unique to South Asian women in the tech industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The road to becoming an engineer in India is paved with grueling exams and fierce competition. One such exam is the Joint Entrance Examination (JEE), which over 1.5 million aspirants attempt annually. Success in this exam opens the doors to prestigious institutions like the Indian Institutes of Technology (IIT). Despite the rising number of female students in these institutions, the gender disparity remains stark, with women comprising only around 20% of the student population.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pursuing a career in engineering often leads South Asian women to seek opportunities abroad. However, this decision is sometimes criticized, as some view immigrants as threats to the local job market. The truth is that many of us choose to leave our home countries due to concerns about safety and the lack of opportunities for professional growth. India has one of the highest rates of sexual assault and related crimes, with a woman being subjected to rape every 15 minutes, according to the National Crime Records Bureau’s 2019 report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next time you meet a South Asian colleague, take the time to talk to them about their experiences and the unique challenges they’ve faced. We all have stories to share, and understanding these challenges can help foster a more inclusive work environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;gallery-box&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;gallery&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/images/aapiblog/aapi1.png&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; alt=&quot;Books&quot; style=&quot;float: left&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even for those who stay in their home countries, the challenges persist. Many South Asian women in tech face the difficult choice of leaving their careers early for various reasons, including child-rearing. In India, for instance, a 2018 World Bank report found that around 20 million women had left the workforce between 2005 and 2018, with a significant proportion citing family responsibilities as the primary reason for their exit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what can be done to bridge this gap and create a more inclusive environment for South Asian women in tech? Mentorship, networking opportunities, and increased visibility are crucial. Organisations like Women Who Code provide invaluable support for women like me, enabling us to connect, learn, and grow in our careers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I continue my journey in the tech industry, I’m committed to using my experiences to help empower the next generation of South Asian women engineers. By sharing our stories and breaking down barriers, we can create a more equitable and diverse tech industry that benefits us all.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
                <pubDate>Tue, 02 May 2023 23:05:55 +0800</pubDate>
                <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/everything-has-beauty-but-not-everyone-can-see</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/everything-has-beauty-but-not-everyone-can-see</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>How Does Techbro Culture Contribute to the Widening Gap in the Tech Industry</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve been a part of the tech industry for years, and recently, I’ve reflected on the impact of tech-bro culture on the widening gap in our field. The struggles faced by my colleagues, friends, and those in the industry have been disheartening, especially as the news of mass layoffs continues to make headlines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I’ve followed the stories of these layoffs, I’ve noticed a stark contrast between the fate of hardworking employees and the rise of tech-bro figures like Sam Bankman Fried, who was involved in the FTX scandal, and Adam Neumann, the founder of WeWork. In the FTX scandal, the company attracted scrutiny for allegedly manipulating the market and exploiting regulatory loopholes, which led to significant losses for investors. Meanwhile, WeWork faced a dramatic fall from grace after its failed IPO attempt in 2019, revealing massive financial mismanagement. Its valuation plummeted from $47 billion to just $2.9 billion in months. It’s troubling to see investors and recruiters prioritize individuals who fit the tech-bro stereotype, even when they lack the necessary skills or experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;gallery-box&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;gallery&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/images/techbro/techbro.png&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; alt=&quot;Books&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tech-bro culture perpetuates the stereotype of nerdy, shorts-wearing male programmers, leading to recruitment biases and the underrepresentation of women and other minority groups. As a part of the industry, I’ve witnessed talented individuals overlooked for roles because they didn’t fit the tech-bro mold. According to a National Center for Women &amp;amp; Information Technology report, women hold only 25% of computing roles in the U.S., and it’s hard not to see the connection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, research has shown that men who fit the tech-bro stereotype are more likely to be hired for engineering positions. A study published in the Journal of Social Issues (DOI: 10.1111/josi.12315) found that participants presented with identical resumes but different photos were more likely to rate male candidates as more competent and hireable if they fit the “nerdy” tech-bro image. This bias not only perpetuates the underrepresentation of diverse talent but also stifles innovation and growth in the industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first step is acknowledging existing biases to bridge the gap and create a more equitable tech industry. Recognizing the problem is crucial to working towards a more diverse and inclusive environment. While there might not be a one-size-fits-all solution, it’s essential to be aware of the situation and have open conversations about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The road to change may be long and challenging, but it is a necessary journey we must embark on to create a more inclusive and equitable future in technology. As we take the time to listen to the stories of those affected by layoffs and the impact of tech-bro culture, let us remember that each individual’s experience is a crucial piece of the larger narrative. Through empathy and understanding, we can truly begin to dismantle the biases that have held us back and work together toward a brighter future for all in the tech industry.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Mon, 10 Apr 2023 20:01:35 +0800</pubDate>
                <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/a-journey-of-a-thousand-leagues-begins-beneath-one-s-feet</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/a-journey-of-a-thousand-leagues-begins-beneath-one-s-feet</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>If Rihanna can make a comeback, why can’t you?</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;Technology is not just a profession; it’s a journey that has its own set of challenges and rewards. Throughout my journey in tech, I’ve experienced both highs and lows. And today, I want to share a personal story with you in hopes of inspiring those who are struggling to find their spark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most engineers, contrary to popular belief, are creative people. We dream big, and we aspire to create tools and software that will disrupt the world. But let’s face it; the tech industry isn’t always sunshine and rainbows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know what it feels like to lose my passion for tech. I worked for a big corporation and had managers who constantly undermined my work and made me feel like I wasn’t good enough. I felt like I was making no impact, and my creative spark started to fade away. It was a difficult time for me. I retracted from community events around the city, even though they would happen in person. I stopped creating random projects or even wanted to read the latest news in tech.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It took me almost a year to realise that it was OK to feel like this, and I did not fail. There is still a spark left in me. I had an epiphany — why not list all the crazy ideas buzzing around in my head? Who knows, they may take years to come to fruition, but that’s the fun part — envisioning them! I’m talking text-to-audio in ANYONE’s voice — Morgan Freeman, Tom Hanks, you name it! And how about making old photos come to life by making them move and talk? Now THAT would be something to see&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I pitched one of my ideas at FOSS Asia, and it was accepted. I created a ChatGPT chrome extension that could change the sentiment of any sentence online with a simple right-click. It was a thrilling moment to have my talk accepted, and it motivated me to believe that there was still light at the end of the tunnel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, to all those struggling to find their spark, keep going. Don’t give up on your dreams. We are in this together. If you need help, reach out to me. Let’s inspire each other to keep dreaming and innovating. Just like our girl RiRi, who went from “Umbrella” to billionaire, you can reignite that spark and achieve greatness.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
                <pubDate>Tue, 07 Mar 2023 20:01:35 +0800</pubDate>
                <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/life-shrinks-or-expands-in-proportion-to-one-s-courage</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/life-shrinks-or-expands-in-proportion-to-one-s-courage</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Running a Technical Community During a Pandemic</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;The pandemic has taken so much away from us. Our lives turned upside down at the start of 2020. Remote work took priority and all of us had to hone our virtual skills. Communities took a major hit too. What once was a place to meet and spend time with folks on meetups had to become an online affair! This meant that all community leaders had to roll up their sleeves and learn how to host events on platforms like Zoom, Topia, or Gather Town, and to maintain and spark conversations on Slack, Discord, etc. Women Who Code is one such community that had to pivot all of its events and conferences online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But do online communities have their perks? Of course, they do. What most community members soon realized is that it was easier to talk to multiple people across innumerable time zones at the same time! We had more connections (virtual) than ever before!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This blog outlines what I learned as a Leadership Fellow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PS: I also added a FAQ section at the end, just in case you need to know how to apply to be a Leadership Fellow&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;gallery-box&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;gallery&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/images/pandemic-community/image_02.jpeg&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; alt=&quot;Table&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/images/pandemic-community/image_04.png&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; alt=&quot;Table&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;!-- &lt;em&gt;Gallery / &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; --&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;positivity&quot;&gt;Positivity&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2020, Women Who Code used a line to help clarify where their movement was at the time. “Being a Connecting Force when the world is being asked to isolate, especially right now.” I think that was the driving force for most communities this past year, and one thing that binds it is “positivity”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, that’s easier said than done. It’s common to find yourself doubting whether your team can execute an event, or wondering if the event will be a success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I have come to realize is that your actions mirror your team. If you seem tense and negative, the team will be demotivated. I have always kept the “biggest smiles” just for the team. I know, it’s a small gesture, but it matters!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;volunteers&quot;&gt;Volunteers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most technical communities are run by volunteers. One thing we often forget is that there is a huge difference between a full-time worker and a volunteer. Firstly, the volunteer is self-motivated. She/He decided to take out time for your organization and help in conducting events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;** Value them**&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means you need to remind them to prioritize their other tasks over their time volunteering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mentally, I often fear I will run out of people to help me. What if I run out of volunteers to help with this event? One of the brilliant things I have noticed about communities is that it’s a movement. So the wheel never stops turning! Help will and can always be found when you believe in the power of people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;applaud-her&quot;&gt;Applaud Her&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fostering of communities is heavily based on feedback and being uplifted. Women Who Code has this amazing “#ApplaudHer” practice. It is basically a way to applaud your members and volunteers when they contribute.I have seen this initiative have a “ripple effect.” Folks from across the community share their #ApplaudHers for one another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;gallery-box&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;gallery&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/images/pandemic-community/applaud_her.jpeg&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; alt=&quot;Books&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;em&gt;Photo by &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/photos/_awzRovsBDU&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;NMG Network&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;feedback-forms&quot;&gt;Feedback Forms&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you really want to run a community, honest feedback is of the utmost importance. I have found that anonymous feedback forms can help the team share their thoughts on where the community is headed. It is equally important to get critical feedback to understand the pain points of your members. So encourage your team members to actively participate and help grow the community! :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;asynchronous-communications&quot;&gt;Asynchronous Communications:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With everyone’s crazy time schedule and time zones all across the world, setting up meetings for discussions can seem like an uphill task. That’s when you need to encourage asynchronous communication between your volunteers. This is to make sure that communications happen continuously even though folks do that at their own pace and time. Dedicate specific applications for certain types of tasks. For example, Trello Boards are great for tracking events and slack is great for conversations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;apps-i-would-recommend&quot;&gt;Apps I would Recommend&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Trello, JIRA Boards: Event Tasks&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Buffer and Hootsuite: Scheduling Social Media Graphics&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Slack, Discord, Zulip: Conversations (1–1, group)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;communicating-through-gifs&quot;&gt;Communicating through GIFs:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the hardest things about an online community is expressing emotions. We use slack for all our communications, but let’s all agree, “texts can be boring,” and it is impossible to talk to your volunteers all the time because we are all in different time zones. So I know this might seem like an obvious trick, but add GIFs to your conversations. It gives volunteers something fun in texting!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;regular-check-ins&quot;&gt;Regular Check-Ins&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although virtual communities force us to be asynchronous, it is also important to check in with your volunteers from time to time to know if the community is able to keep up with their aspirations. Most volunteers expect a community to aid in their growth. This can either be through increasing their networking circle, their technical skills, or their brand. Check-in and say hi every few months and make sure your volunteers are able to meet their goals from the community too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;never-underestimate-automation&quot;&gt;Never Underestimate Automation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being in the field of technology and software engineering, we are not new to “automation.” Most of us love finding mundane tasks and automating them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find community development to be a field that constantly requires automation. Another advantage is that if you are able to simplify everyday tasks, you can focus your attention on other tasks at hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this section, I will discuss various ways in which I automated applications or services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;slackbot&quot;&gt;Slackbot&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slackbot has a variety of functionalities. One awesome use is the remind command. This can be used to set up automated messages on slack related to events and regular check-ins&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Emails
Community emails can often center around a few themes. This can range from “How to join” or inquiries about the events/teams. It is best to create email templates for these topics and use them regularly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zoom&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zoom has an email settings feature. This can be used to add specific emails to registrants of an event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, our community used to get emails from participants after every event, asking about the Youtube Recording. So I added the link to the Youtube Playlist on the emails sent out to attendees and participants who missed the event. Simple tricks like that can help save a lot of time!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;gallery-box&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;gallery&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/images/pandemic-community/slackbot.jpeg&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; alt=&quot;Table&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/images/pandemic-community/zoom.jpeg&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; alt=&quot;Table&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;!-- &lt;em&gt;Gallery / &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; --&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This blog gives a quick and general overview of running a virtual track. I learned so much more from my time at Women Who Code Python and Cloud. From solving Conflict Resolutions to motivating my team of volunteers, to maintaining a code of conduct on zoom, the list just goes on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Would I recommend this role?&lt;/strong&gt;
YES OF COURSE! I was an Engineer in my day job and never gave a second thought about communities in the long term!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used to love mentoring and reviewing proposals, organizing a few technical talks from time to time. But all of my work was highly technical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I never believed that I could expand and manage an online community, let alone during a pandemic! But I loved every bit of it, it made me care more about women in tech and the journey to increase our representation!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;faq-section-leadership-fellow&quot;&gt;FAQ Section: Leadership Fellow&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What is a Leadership Fellow at Women Who Code?&lt;/em&gt;
As a Leadership Fellow at Women Who Code, you get to practice leadership skills. This means you get to learn skills like “Presence, Learning, Inclusivity” etc during the course of 1 year where you get to work with technical tracks at Women Who Code&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What are the responsibilities of a Leadership Fellow?&lt;/em&gt;
As a Leadership Fellow, you are assigned technical tracks. This means you get to lead a team of volunteers at your respective track and conduct technical events across the year. Along with this, the global team helps you hone your leadership skills and actively apply them to prosper your community.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Where do I apply?&lt;/em&gt;
Stay in touch with Women Who Code and sign up as a member! The application form is shared with members on newsletters and social media too.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What are the steps of the application? What can I expect from my interview?&lt;/em&gt;
During 2020, there were a few steps to the process of becoming a Fellow. The first step was filling out the application form. This had a few descriptive questions on past experiences.
If you qualified for the second step, this included preparing technical materials in the women who code template format. After this, the third round was interviews with the Leadership Directors at Women Who Code’s Global Team. The last round was a 1–1 interview with the CTO Joey Rosenberg.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please feel free to &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;mailto:varchanaiyer139@gmail.com&quot;&gt;reach out&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; to me with any questions about this!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jul 2021 20:01:35 +0800</pubDate>
                <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/remember-that-happiness-is-a-way-of-travel-not-a-destination</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/remember-that-happiness-is-a-way-of-travel-not-a-destination</guid>
                
                
            </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>